<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.2.2">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://ukrainians.nl/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://ukrainians.nl/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2025-11-10T22:20:31+00:00</updated><id>https://ukrainians.nl/index.xml</id><title type="html">Stichting Oekraïners in Nederland / Ukrainians in the Netherlands Foundation</title><subtitle>Ukrainians in the Netherlands Foundation (Stichting Oekraïners in Nederland) is a non-profit platform established in 2014 to support the needs of the Dutch Ukrainian diaspora.</subtitle><entry><title type="html">Традиційне святкування Дня Незалежності України в Нідерландах</title><link href="https://ukrainians.nl/uniting-boats-traditional-celebration-of-ukraines-independence-day-in-the-netherlands" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Традиційне святкування Дня Незалежності України в Нідерландах" /><published>2025-08-24T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-08-24T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://ukrainians.nl/uniting-boats-traditional-celebration-of-ukraines-independence-day-in-the-netherlands</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://ukrainians.nl/uniting-boats-traditional-celebration-of-ukraines-independence-day-in-the-netherlands"><![CDATA[<h2>🇺🇦</h2>

<p>24 серпня 2025-го року українська громада в Нідерландах відзначила День Незалежності України не лише молитвою й офіційними промовами, а й традиційним святкуванням “на човнах”. Захід був організований Фундацією «Українці в Нідерландах».
У Гаазі, Гронінгені, Харлемі та Маастрихті десятки човнів із синьо-жовтими прапорами вирушили у святковий заплив. Канали голландських міст цього дня зазвучали українськими піснями, сміхом і розмовами, а вишиванки та стрічки створили особливу атмосферу єдності.</p>

<p>📍 У <strong>Гронінгені</strong> святкування розпочалося з молитви та промови представника Посольства України, після чого учасники вирушили у спільну подорож каналами міста.</p>

<p><img class="img-fluid mt-25" src="/assets/img/events/2025-08-24-uniting-boats-traditional-celebration-of-ukraines-independence-day-in-the-netherlands/groningen2.webp" />
<img class="img-fluid mt-25" src="/assets/img/events/2025-08-24-uniting-boats-traditional-celebration-of-ukraines-independence-day-in-the-netherlands/groningen3.webp" />
<img class="img-fluid mt-25" src="/assets/img/events/2025-08-24-uniting-boats-traditional-celebration-of-ukraines-independence-day-in-the-netherlands/groningen4.webp" /></p>

<p>📍 У <strong>Гаазі</strong> після Всеукраїнського молебню за Україну та виступів почесних гостей також долучилися до традиції — човни з українськими діаспорянами проплили каналами міста.</p>

<p><img class="img-fluid mt-25" src="/assets/img/events/2025-08-24-uniting-boats-traditional-celebration-of-ukraines-independence-day-in-the-netherlands/the-hague1.webp" />
<img class="img-fluid mt-25" src="/assets/img/events/2025-08-24-uniting-boats-traditional-celebration-of-ukraines-independence-day-in-the-netherlands/the-hague2.webp" />
<img class="img-fluid mt-25" src="/assets/img/events/2025-08-24-uniting-boats-traditional-celebration-of-ukraines-independence-day-in-the-netherlands/the-hague3.webp" />
<img class="img-fluid mt-25" src="/assets/img/events/2025-08-24-uniting-boats-traditional-celebration-of-ukraines-independence-day-in-the-netherlands/the-hague4.webp" /></p>

<p>📍 У <strong>Харлемі</strong> українці також долучились до запливів каналами міста, прикрасивши човни прапорами та символікою. Тут святкування мало затишний і дружній характер: родини та друзі зібралися разом, щоб у невимушеній атмосфері відчути єдність і радість незалежності. Дякуємо за співорганізаторство партнеру – <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/company/haarlem4ukraine/">ГО Haarlem For Ukraine</a>.</p>

<p><img class="img-fluid mt-25" src="/assets/img/events/2025-08-24-uniting-boats-traditional-celebration-of-ukraines-independence-day-in-the-netherlands/haarlem1.webp" />
<img class="img-fluid mt-25" src="/assets/img/events/2025-08-24-uniting-boats-traditional-celebration-of-ukraines-independence-day-in-the-netherlands/haarlem2.webp" />
<img class="img-fluid mt-25" src="/assets/img/events/2025-08-24-uniting-boats-traditional-celebration-of-ukraines-independence-day-in-the-netherlands/haarlem3.webp" />
<img class="img-fluid mt-25" src="/assets/img/events/2025-08-24-uniting-boats-traditional-celebration-of-ukraines-independence-day-in-the-netherlands/haarlem4.webp" /></p>

<p>📍 У <strong>Маастрихті</strong> заплив став яскравим свідченням згуртованості громади на півдні Нідерландів. Учасники поділилися теплими словами, українськими піснями та смаколиками, створивши відчуття маленького шматочка України далеко від дому. Дякуємо за співпрацю партнерам – <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/company/ukrainian-house-in-maastricht/">ГО Український дім в Маастрихті</a>.</p>

<p><img class="img-fluid mt-25" src="/assets/img/events/2025-08-24-uniting-boats-traditional-celebration-of-ukraines-independence-day-in-the-netherlands/maastricht1.webp" />
<img class="img-fluid mt-25" src="/assets/img/events/2025-08-24-uniting-boats-traditional-celebration-of-ukraines-independence-day-in-the-netherlands/maastricht2.webp" />
<img class="img-fluid mt-25" src="/assets/img/events/2025-08-24-uniting-boats-traditional-celebration-of-ukraines-independence-day-in-the-netherlands/maastricht3.webp" />
<img class="img-fluid mt-25" src="/assets/img/events/2025-08-24-uniting-boats-traditional-celebration-of-ukraines-independence-day-in-the-netherlands/maastricht4.webp" /></p>

<p>Цей день нагадав нам, що незалежність — це не лише державний статус, а й щоденна присутність України у серцях її людей, де б вони не були.
💙💛 Дякуємо всім, хто долучився до організації та святкування, і чекаємо на наступні зустрічі української громади в Нідерландах!
Окрема вдячність <a href="https://www.rijksoverheid.nl/ministeries/ministerie-van-asiel-en-migratie">Міністерству з питань притулку та міграції Нідерландів (Ministerie van Asiel en Migratie)</a> за підтримку заходів.</p>

<h2 id="-1">🇬🇧</h2>

<p>2On 24 August, the Ukrainian community in the Netherlands celebrated Ukraine’s Independence Day not only with prayers and official speeches but also with the traditional boat cruises. The event was organised by the Ukrainians in the Netherlands Foundation.
In The Hague, Groningen, Haarlem and Maastricht, dozens of boats with blue-and-yellow flags set off on festive journeys. The canals of Dutch cities were filled with Ukrainian songs, laughter and conversations, while embroidered shirts and ribbons created a special atmosphere of unity.</p>

<p>📍 In <strong>Groningen</strong>, the celebration began with a prayer and a speech from the representative of the Embassy of Ukraine, after which participants embarked on a shared voyage through the city’s canals.</p>

<p><img class="img-fluid mt-25" src="/assets/img/events/2025-08-24-uniting-boats-traditional-celebration-of-ukraines-independence-day-in-the-netherlands/groningen2.webp" />
<img class="img-fluid mt-25" src="/assets/img/events/2025-08-24-uniting-boats-traditional-celebration-of-ukraines-independence-day-in-the-netherlands/groningen3.webp" />
<img class="img-fluid mt-25" src="/assets/img/events/2025-08-24-uniting-boats-traditional-celebration-of-ukraines-independence-day-in-the-netherlands/groningen4.webp" /></p>

<p>📍 In <strong>The Hague</strong>, after the All-Ukrainian prayer service for Ukraine and the speeches of honoured guests, the community also joined the tradition — boats with Ukrainians traveled through the canals of the city.</p>

<p><img class="img-fluid mt-25" src="/assets/img/events/2025-08-24-uniting-boats-traditional-celebration-of-ukraines-independence-day-in-the-netherlands/the-hague1.webp" />
<img class="img-fluid mt-25" src="/assets/img/events/2025-08-24-uniting-boats-traditional-celebration-of-ukraines-independence-day-in-the-netherlands/the-hague2.webp" />
<img class="img-fluid mt-25" src="/assets/img/events/2025-08-24-uniting-boats-traditional-celebration-of-ukraines-independence-day-in-the-netherlands/the-hague3.webp" />
<img class="img-fluid mt-25" src="/assets/img/events/2025-08-24-uniting-boats-traditional-celebration-of-ukraines-independence-day-in-the-netherlands/the-hague4.webp" /></p>

<p>📍 In <strong>Haarlem</strong>, Ukrainians also took to the city’s canals, decorating the boats with flags and national symbols. The celebration there had a cosy and friendly atmosphere: families and friends gathered together to feel the unity and joy of independence in an informal setting. We thank our partners <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/company/haarlem4ukraine/">NGO Haarlem For Ukraine</a> for partnering in organising this event in Haarlem.</p>

<p><img class="img-fluid mt-25" src="/assets/img/events/2025-08-24-uniting-boats-traditional-celebration-of-ukraines-independence-day-in-the-netherlands/haarlem1.webp" />
<img class="img-fluid mt-25" src="/assets/img/events/2025-08-24-uniting-boats-traditional-celebration-of-ukraines-independence-day-in-the-netherlands/haarlem2.webp" />
<img class="img-fluid mt-25" src="/assets/img/events/2025-08-24-uniting-boats-traditional-celebration-of-ukraines-independence-day-in-the-netherlands/haarlem3.webp" />
<img class="img-fluid mt-25" src="/assets/img/events/2025-08-24-uniting-boats-traditional-celebration-of-ukraines-independence-day-in-the-netherlands/haarlem4.webp" /></p>

<p>📍 In <strong>Maastricht</strong>, the boat rally became a vivid testimony of the community’s solidarity in the south of the Netherlands. Participants shared warm words, Ukrainian songs and homemade treats, creating the feeling of a small piece of Ukraine far away from home. We thank our partners <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/company/ukrainian-house-in-maastricht/">NGO Ukrainian House in Maastricht</a> for partnering in organising this event in Maastricht.</p>

<p><img class="img-fluid mt-25" src="/assets/img/events/2025-08-24-uniting-boats-traditional-celebration-of-ukraines-independence-day-in-the-netherlands/maastricht1.webp" />
<img class="img-fluid mt-25" src="/assets/img/events/2025-08-24-uniting-boats-traditional-celebration-of-ukraines-independence-day-in-the-netherlands/maastricht2.webp" />
<img class="img-fluid mt-25" src="/assets/img/events/2025-08-24-uniting-boats-traditional-celebration-of-ukraines-independence-day-in-the-netherlands/maastricht3.webp" />
<img class="img-fluid mt-25" src="/assets/img/events/2025-08-24-uniting-boats-traditional-celebration-of-ukraines-independence-day-in-the-netherlands/maastricht4.webp" /></p>

<p>This day reminded us that independence is not only a state status but also the daily presence of Ukraine in the hearts of its people, wherever they may be.
💙💛 We thank everyone who organized and  joined the celebration and look forward to the next gatherings of the Ukrainian community in the Netherlands!
Special thanks to the Ministry of <a href="https://www.rijksoverheid.nl/ministeries/ministerie-van-asiel-en-migratie">Asylum and Migration of the Netherlands (Ministerie van Asiel en Migratie)</a> for supporting the events.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="events" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[🇺🇦]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Заява Фундації «Українці в Нідерландах» щодо Закону України №4555 (законопроєкт №12414)</title><link href="https://ukrainians.nl/zaiava_fundatsii_shchodo_zakonu_ukrayiny_no4555_zakonoproekt_no12414" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Заява Фундації «Українці в Нідерландах» щодо Закону України №4555 (законопроєкт №12414)" /><published>2025-07-24T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-07-24T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://ukrainians.nl/zaiava_fundatsii_shchodo_zakonu_ukrayiny_no4555_zakonoproekt_no12414</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://ukrainians.nl/zaiava_fundatsii_shchodo_zakonu_ukrayiny_no4555_zakonoproekt_no12414"><![CDATA[<p>Фундація «Українці в Нідерландах» уважно стежить за подіями, пов’язаними з нещодавніми змінами в законодавстві щодо незалежності Національного антикорупційного бюро України (НАБУ) та Спеціалізованої антикорупційної прокуратури (САП), зокрема Законом України №4555 (законопроєкт №12414).</p>

<p>Цей закон не лише може посилити корупційні ризики, а й ставить під сумнів подальшу євроінтеграцію України. Ми також відзначаємо зростання громадського невдоволення через неефективне використання бюджетних коштів під час війни та нерозв’язані питання, пов’язані з корупцією й несправедливістю.</p>

<p>Ми закликаємо народних депутатів України розробити законопроєкт, який відновить незалежність НАБУ та САП, і очікуємо ефективного голосування за нього у Верховній Раді та подальшого підписання Президентом України. Ми також закликаємо до впровадження заходів, що сприятимуть підвищенню ефективності роботи антикорупційних органів, адже корупція підриває обороноздатність країни й завдає шкоди українському суспільству загалом.</p>

<p>Фундація «Українці в Нідерландах» також закликає громадян в Україні та діаспору до виваженості й дій виключно в межах правового поля, визначеного Конституцією України. Ми закликаємо до конструктивної взаємодії з народними депутатами, обраними у відповідних округах, з політичними партіями, представленими у Верховній Раді України ІХ скликання, а також до створення відповідних електронних петицій до Президента України.</p>

<p>Команда Фундації покладається на зрілість і відповідальність громадянського суспільства у ставленні до чутливих тем, зокрема незалежності антикорупційних органів, і розраховує на усвідомлення додаткових ризиків, що виникають у період соціально-політичної турбулентності під час війни.</p>

<p>З вірою в перемогу й демократію,
Рада правління Фундації «Українці в Нідерландах»</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="press" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Фундація «Українці в Нідерландах» уважно стежить за подіями, пов’язаними з нещодавніми змінами в законодавстві щодо незалежності Національного антикорупційного бюро України (НАБУ) та Спеціалізованої антикорупційної прокуратури (САП), зокрема Законом України №4555 (законопроєкт №12414).]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Ukraine’s Independence Day Boat Celebration in The Hague: Over a 10-Year Tradition of Unity and Support</title><link href="https://ukrainians.nl/ukraine-s-independence-day-celebration-on-the-canals-of-the-hague" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Ukraine’s Independence Day Boat Celebration in The Hague: Over a 10-Year Tradition of Unity and Support" /><published>2025-07-09T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-07-09T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://ukrainians.nl/ukraine-s-independence-day-celebration-on-the-canals-of-the-hague</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://ukrainians.nl/ukraine-s-independence-day-celebration-on-the-canals-of-the-hague"><![CDATA[<p>Ukraine’s Independence Day Boat Celebration in The Hague: Over a 10-Year Tradition of Unity and Support
Every year, on the occasion of Ukraine’s Independence Day, the Ukrainians in the Netherlands Foundation organises a symbolic boat parade through the canals of The Hague — a vibrant event that brings the Ukrainian community together around shared identity and support for Ukraine.</p>

<p>In this way, they want the Dutch to see, hear, and feel Ukraine.</p>

<p>Participants decorate boats with blue and yellow flags, wear traditional embroidered shirts (vyshyvankas), sing Ukrainian songs, and conclude the event with a collective performance of the national anthem right in the middle of the canal.
This tradition began in 2014 and is led by the Foundation’s Chair, Vira Zwan, and Board Member Liudmyla Lisovska.
The celebration is regularly attended by the Ambassador of Ukraine to the Netherlands, embassy staff, and the Honorary Consul Karel Dirven.</p>

<p>📌 Highlights of the event:</p>

<ul>
  <li>Boat parade through the canals of The Hague with Ukrainian flags, songs, and floral wreaths.</li>
  <li>Ukrainians dressed in traditional attire, waving national flags.</li>
  <li>The national anthem of Ukraine sung together on the water.</li>
  <li>Organised by the Ukrainians in the Netherlands Foundation.</li>
  <li>A charitable initiative — all donations go to support Ukraine.</li>
</ul>

<p>All the announcements and reports are on our official website, <a href="https://www.instagram.com/ukrainians_nl">Instagram</a>, and community messenger channels.</p>

<hr />

<p>Media about us:
<a href="https://www.ukrinform.ua/amp/rubric-society/2767087-svatkuvanna-dna-nezaleznosti-v-niderlandah-zapliv-kanalami-gaagi.html">Ukraine’s Independence Day celebration on the canals of The Hague</a></p>

<p>🇺🇦🇺🇦🇺🇦</p>

<h2 id="день-незалежності-україни-на-човнах-у-гаазі-традиція-єдності-та-підтримки-якій-більше-10-років">День Незалежності України на човнах у Гаазі: традиція єдності та підтримки, якій більше 10 років</h2>

<p>Щороку до Дня Незалежності України фундація «Українці в Нідерландах» організовує символічний заплив каналами Гааги — яскраву подію, що об’єднує українську громаду навколо спільної ідентичності та підтримки України.
Учасники заходу прикрашають човни жовто-блакитними прапорами, одягають вишиванки, співають українські пісні й завершують подію урочистим виконанням Державного гімну посеред каналу.
Цю ініціативу започатковано у 2014 році за участі голови фундації Віри Зван та Людмили Лісовської, членкині Ради правління Фундації.
До святкування традиційно долучаються Посол України в Нідерландах, співробітники Посольства, а також почесний консул Нідерландів Карел Дірвен.</p>

<p>📌 Основні моменти заходу:</p>

<ul>
  <li>Заплив каналами Гааги у вишиванках, із прапорами, вінками, піснями.</li>
  <li>Символічна єдність української громади за кордоном.</li>
  <li>Благодійна мета: зібрані кошти спрямовуються на допомогу Україні.</li>
  <li>Організатор — фундація «Українці в Нідерландах».</li>
</ul>

<p>Анонси та звіти — на офіційному сайті фундації, <a href="https://www.instagram.com/ukrainians_nl">Instagram</a> та в усіх месенджерах спільноти.</p>

<p><img src="/assets/img/events/2025-07-10-ukraine-s-independence-day-celebration-on-the-canals-of-the-hague/ukraine-s-independence-day-celebration-on-the-canals-of-the-hague-02.webp" class="img-fluid mt-25" />
<img src="/assets/img/events/2025-07-10-ukraine-s-independence-day-celebration-on-the-canals-of-the-hague/ukraine-s-independence-day-celebration-on-the-canals-of-the-hague-03.webp" class="img-fluid mt-25" />
<img src="/assets/img/events/2025-07-10-ukraine-s-independence-day-celebration-on-the-canals-of-the-hague/ukraine-s-independence-day-celebration-on-the-canals-of-the-hague-04.webp" class="img-fluid mt-25" />
<img src="/assets/img/events/2025-07-10-ukraine-s-independence-day-celebration-on-the-canals-of-the-hague/ukraine-s-independence-day-celebration-on-the-canals-of-the-hague-05.webp" class="img-fluid mt-25" />
<img src="/assets/img/events/2025-07-10-ukraine-s-independence-day-celebration-on-the-canals-of-the-hague/ukraine-s-independence-day-celebration-on-the-canals-of-the-hague-06.webp" class="img-fluid mt-25" />
<img src="/assets/img/events/2025-07-10-ukraine-s-independence-day-celebration-on-the-canals-of-the-hague/ukraine-s-independence-day-celebration-on-the-canals-of-the-hague-07.webp" class="img-fluid mt-25" />
<img src="/assets/img/events/2025-07-10-ukraine-s-independence-day-celebration-on-the-canals-of-the-hague/ukraine-s-independence-day-celebration-on-the-canals-of-the-hague-08.webp" class="img-fluid mt-25" /></p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="events" /><category term="events" /><category term="Hague" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Ukraine’s Independence Day Boat Celebration in The Hague: Over a 10-Year Tradition of Unity and Support Every year, on the occasion of Ukraine’s Independence Day, the Ukrainians in the Netherlands Foundation organises a symbolic boat parade through the canals of The Hague — a vibrant event that brings the Ukrainian community together around shared identity and support for Ukraine.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">De jaarrekening van de Stichting 2023, 2024</title><link href="https://ukrainians.nl/jaarrekening-2024" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="De jaarrekening van de Stichting 2023, 2024" /><published>2025-07-01T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-07-01T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://ukrainians.nl/jaarrekening-2024</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://ukrainians.nl/jaarrekening-2024"><![CDATA[<div class="row text-center">
<div class="col-12 mt-50">

<a href="https://ukrainians.nl/assets/pdf/jaarrekening-2023.pdf" style="
border-radius: var(--border-radius);
border: 1px solid var(--text-color);
color: var(--text-color);
padding: 1em;
margin: 1em;
">
<i class="far fa-file-pdf" style="font-size: 2em;"></i>&nbsp; Jaarrekening 2023
</a>

</div>

<div class="col-12 mt-50">

<a href="https://ukrainians.nl/assets/pdf/tussentijdse-cijfers-per-30-juni-2024.pdf" style="
border-radius: var(--border-radius);
border: 1px solid var(--text-color);
color: var(--text-color);
padding: 1em;
margin: 1em;
">
<i class="far fa-file-pdf" style="font-size: 2em;"></i>&nbsp; Tussentijdse cijfers per 30 juni 2024
</a>

</div>
</div>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="press" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">A Symbolic Gesture in The Hague: Defence Ministers Stand with Ukraine on the Peace Square</title><link href="https://ukrainians.nl/defence-ministers-stand-with-ukraine" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="A Symbolic Gesture in The Hague: Defence Ministers Stand with Ukraine on the Peace Square" /><published>2025-06-25T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-06-25T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://ukrainians.nl/defence-ministers-stand-with-ukraine</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://ukrainians.nl/defence-ministers-stand-with-ukraine"><![CDATA[<p>On 23 June, on the eve of the historic 2025 NATO Summit, a peaceful demonstration took place in front of the 🕊️ Peace Palace in The Hague. Organised by the Ukrainian and Lithuanian communities, the event aimed to show solidarity with the North Atlantic Alliance and affirm Ukraine’s unwavering aspiration to become a full member. It also served as a civic signal: the decisions made at this summit matter — for Ukraine, for Europe, and for global security. 🌍</p>

<p>The central messages of the rally were:</p>

<p>🔹 “Thank you, NATO, for supporting Ukraine”
🔹 “NATO is stronger with Ukraine”
🔹 “Ukraine’s future is in NATO”
🔹 “Ukraine’s NATO membership is inevitable”</p>

<p>Participants held Ukrainisn, Lithuanian and Dutch flags, along with signs calling for unity, responsibility, and collective security. The image was one of determination — a street-level reflection of the values NATO claims to protect.</p>

<p>Two high-ranking guests addressed the crowd:
Ruben Brekelmans, Minister of Defence of the Netherlands, and
Dovilė Šakalienė, Minister of Defence of Lithuania.</p>

<p>“For the first time in history, Alliance countries will commit to spending 5% on defence,” said Ruben Brekelmans.
“I understand why you feel the urgency. What’s happening in Ukraine could happen in Lithuania or anywhere in Eastern Europe. It’s a reminder to all of us in NATO of what’s at stake.”</p>

<p>“Ukraine is Europe. And Europe needs Ukraine’s experience, expertise, and industrial strength,” said Minister Šakalienė.
“This isn’t just support — it’s shared responsibility for the future of democracies.”</p>

<hr />

<p>🇺🇦🇺🇦🇺🇦</p>

<p>Символічний жест у Гаазі: міністри оборони підтримали Україну просто на площі біля
Палацу миру</p>

<p>23 червня, напередодні історичного саміту НАТО 2025, біля Палацу миру в Гаазі відбулася мирна акція, організована українською та литовською громадами. Метою заходу було продемонструвати підтримку Північноатлантичному альянсу та рішучість України стати його повноцінним членом та надати громадський сигнал про важливість рішень, які ухвалюються на саміті.</p>

<p>Ключовими гаслами акції були:</p>

<p>🔹 «Дякуємо, НАТО, за підтримку України»
🔹 «З Україною NATO сильніше»
🔹 «Майбутнє України в НАТО»
🔹 «Членство України в НАТО невідворотні».</p>

<p>Учасники тримали прапори України, Литви та Нідерландів, а також плакати з промовистими гаслами про єдність, безпеку та відповідальність.</p>

<p>Під час мітингу до активістів звернулись Рубен Брекелманс, міністр оборони Нідерландів та Довіле Шакалієне, міністерка оборони Литви.</p>

<p>«Вперше в історії країни Альянсу візьмуть на себе зобов’язання витрачати 5% на оборону,» — заявив Рубен Брекелманс. — «Я розумію, чому ви відчуваєте терміновість. Те, що відбувається в Україні, може статися в Литві чи будь-де у Східній Європі. Це нагадування нам усім у НАТО — що поставлено на карту.»</p>

<p>«Україна — це Європа. І Європі потрібні український досвід, знання та промисловий потенціал. Це не просто підтримка — це співучасть у майбутньому демократій,» — звернулась до громади Довіле Шакалієне, Міністерка оборони Литви.</p>

<p><img src="/assets/img/events/2025-06-25-defence-ministers-stand-with-ukraine/1.webp" class="img-fluid mt-25" />
<img src="/assets/img/events/2025-06-25-defence-ministers-stand-with-ukraine/2.webp" class="img-fluid mt-25" />
<img src="/assets/img/events/2025-06-25-defence-ministers-stand-with-ukraine/3.webp" class="img-fluid mt-25" />
<img src="/assets/img/events/2025-06-25-defence-ministers-stand-with-ukraine/5.webp" class="img-fluid mt-25" />
<img src="/assets/img/events/2025-06-25-defence-ministers-stand-with-ukraine/6.webp" class="img-fluid mt-25" />
<img src="/assets/img/events/2025-06-25-defence-ministers-stand-with-ukraine/7.webp" class="img-fluid mt-25" /></p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="events" /><category term="events" /><category term="Hague" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[On 23 June, on the eve of the historic 2025 NATO Summit, a peaceful demonstration took place in front of the 🕊️ Peace Palace in The Hague. Organised by the Ukrainian and Lithuanian communities, the event aimed to show solidarity with the North Atlantic Alliance and affirm Ukraine’s unwavering aspiration to become a full member. It also served as a civic signal: the decisions made at this summit matter — for Ukraine, for Europe, and for global security. 🌍]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Welcome Ukraine 🇺🇦</title><link href="https://ukrainians.nl/welcome-ukraine" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Welcome Ukraine 🇺🇦" /><published>2025-05-11T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-05-11T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://ukrainians.nl/welcome-ukraine</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://ukrainians.nl/welcome-ukraine"><![CDATA[<p>«Welcome Ukraine 🇺🇦» — is the biggest event of this spring ‘s-Hertogenbosch, dedicated to Ukraine!</p>

<p>On 29 of May 2025 for the second time, ‘s-Hertogenbosch will welcome Ukrainians and their friends, who are supporting Ukraine through this difficult time of full scale invasion. Parade square near the Parochie Sint-Janskathedraal church will embrace everyone to show solidarity, devotion to the struggle of Ukrainian people.
Join us! 🌻</p>

<ul>
  <li>📅  Date: 29.05.2025</li>
  <li>🕰️ Time: 13:00-18:30</li>
  <li>📍Location: Parade,  ‘s-Hertogenbosch</li>
  <li>🎯 free of charge</li>
</ul>

<p>This heartfelt meeting is dedicated to 110 thousand Ukrainian refugees: opening of the event, speeches from official representatives, worships by Dutch and Ukrainian priests, choirs: Makivka and Korali. It might be a great experience for everyone, because you not only will greet your old friends, but might also meet new! You can become a part of a big march with Ukrainian flag, and a concert performed by famous Ukrainian artists!</p>

<p>The program of the day:</p>

<ul>
  <li>official opening ceremony of the action on Parade Square, ‘s-Hertogenbosch at 13:00</li>
  <li>general march with Ukrainian flag 🇺🇦 ;</li>
  <li>church service in Sint-Janskathedraal🙏;</li>
  <li>grand concert with the participation of famous Ukrainian singers: Oleh Skrypka &amp; VV, Patsyki z Franyka, Ivan Navi, and Veronika Morska.</li>
</ul>

<p>«Welcome Ukraine 🇺🇦» event will be attended by the Ukrainian ambassador and honorary consul, representatives of the city community, Ukrainian military personnel, famous Ukrainian singers, and choirs.</p>

<p>Join us with your families and local friends. We will be happy to meet you at the event, wearing embroidered shirts and with Ukrainian flags! Together we are strong! Slava Ukraine!</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="events" /><category term="events" /><category term="‘s-Hertogenbosch" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[«Welcome Ukraine 🇺🇦» — is the biggest event of this spring ‘s-Hertogenbosch, dedicated to Ukraine!]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Powering Defence: Generators and Charging Stations Delivered to Ukraine</title><link href="https://ukrainians.nl/powering-defence-generators-and-charging-stations-delivered-to-ukraine" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Powering Defence: Generators and Charging Stations Delivered to Ukraine" /><published>2025-02-06T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-02-06T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://ukrainians.nl/powering-defence-generators-and-charging-stations-delivered-to-ukraine</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://ukrainians.nl/powering-defence-generators-and-charging-stations-delivered-to-ukraine"><![CDATA[<p>Thanks to the joint efforts of the Ukrainians in the Netherlands
Foundation and representatives of the Crimean Tatar community, we
successfully purchased and delivered essential equipment to support
Ukrainian defenders.</p>

<p>What was delivered?</p>

<p>– ✅ 2 inverter generators (KS 2100 IG S)</p>

<p>– ✅ 2 EcoFlow Delta 2 charging stations</p>

<p>This equipment has been delivered to the area, where reliable power
supply is critical for maintaining communications, operations, and
safety.</p>

<p>💰 Financial Report:</p>

<p>– €1,138 – generators</p>

<p>– €1,598 – charging stations</p>

<p>📌 Funding Source:</p>

<p>These items were purchased using donations collected during the Embassy
Festival held on 7 September 2024 in The Hague.</p>

<p>🙏 Special Thanks:</p>

<p>We extend heartfelt thanks to Mykhailo and Vasyl for their free and
prompt delivery. Your contribution goes far beyond logistics — it is
real and timely help for those protecting our country.</p>

<p>Together, we stand with Ukraine. Every action counts.</p>

<p>Crimea is Ukraine!</p>

<p><strong><em>– February 6, 2025</em></strong></p>

<p><img src="/assets/img/events/2025-02-06-powering-defence-generators-and-charging-stations-delivered-to-ukraine/media/image2.jpg" class="img-thumbnail margined" /></p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="humanitarian" /><category term="humanitarian" /><category term="aid" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Thanks to the joint efforts of the Ukrainians in the Netherlands Foundation and representatives of the Crimean Tatar community, we successfully purchased and delivered essential equipment to support Ukrainian defenders.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">One Year of Solidarity: Over €185,000 Raised for Ukraine (Feb 2023 – Feb 2024)</title><link href="https://ukrainians.nl/one-year-of-solidarity-over-185-000-raised-for-ukraine-feb-2023-feb-2024" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="One Year of Solidarity: Over €185,000 Raised for Ukraine (Feb 2023 – Feb 2024)" /><published>2024-03-10T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-03-10T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://ukrainians.nl/one-year-of-solidarity-over-185-000-raised-for-ukraine-feb-2023-feb-2024-</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://ukrainians.nl/one-year-of-solidarity-over-185-000-raised-for-ukraine-feb-2023-feb-2024"><![CDATA[<p>10 March 2024 — Over the course of one year, from 24 February 2023 to
24 February 2024, the Ukrainians in the Netherlands Foundation has
continued its dedicated work to support Ukrainians affected by Russia’s
full-scale invasion.</p>

<p>In that time, we successfully raised €185,040 and delivered thousands of
kilograms of urgently needed humanitarian aid to families, frontline
responders, and vulnerable communities across Ukraine.</p>

<p>Thanks to the generosity of our donors and partners, we were able to
send:</p>

<ul>
  <li>🛍️ 7,454 kg of essential items for displaced persons</li>
  <li>🐶 3,079 kg of pet supplies</li>
  <li>🧴 1,177 kg of hygiene products</li>
  <li>👚 4,081 kg of clothing</li>
  <li>🍏 9,112 kg of food</li>
  <li>🧸 1,212 kg of children’s goods</li>
  <li>💻 2,372 electronic devices</li>
  <li>💊 14,567 kg of medicines</li>
  <li>🚗 12 vehicles for transporting aid and saving lives</li>
</ul>

<p>We are proud of what has been achieved — but we know the work is far
from over.</p>

<p>🕊️ This is a long and difficult battle, but together we move steadily
forward toward victory.</p>

<p>👉 We invite everyone who cares about Ukraine to join us — by
donating, volunteering, or helping spread the word. Every action
matters. Every voice counts.</p>

<p>Together, we are stronger. Let us keep fighting — and we will
overcome. 🇺🇦</p>

<p>Ukrainians in the Netherlands Foundation – Stichting Oekraïners in
Nederland</p>

<p><strong><em>– March 10, 2024</em></strong></p>

<p><img src="/assets/img/events/2024-03-10-one-year-of-solidarity-over-185-000-raised-for-ukraine-feb-2023-feb-2024-/media/image2.jpg" class="img-thumbnail margined" />
<img src="/assets/img/events/2024-03-10-one-year-of-solidarity-over-185-000-raised-for-ukraine-feb-2023-feb-2024-/media/image3.jpg" class="img-thumbnail margined" />
<img src="/assets/img/events/2024-03-10-one-year-of-solidarity-over-185-000-raised-for-ukraine-feb-2023-feb-2024-/media/image4.jpg" class="img-thumbnail margined" />
<img src="/assets/img/events/2024-03-10-one-year-of-solidarity-over-185-000-raised-for-ukraine-feb-2023-feb-2024-/media/image5.jpg" class="img-thumbnail margined" /></p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="humanitarian" /><category term="humanitarian" /><category term="aid" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[10 March 2024 — Over the course of one year, from 24 February 2023 to 24 February 2024, the Ukrainians in the Netherlands Foundation has continued its dedicated work to support Ukrainians affected by Russia’s full-scale invasion.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Modern Medical Equipment Delivered to Chernivtsi Children’s Hospital</title><link href="https://ukrainians.nl/modern-medical-equipment-delivered-to-chernivtsi-children-s-hospital" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Modern Medical Equipment Delivered to Chernivtsi Children’s Hospital" /><published>2024-03-10T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-03-10T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://ukrainians.nl/modern-medical-equipment-delivered-to-chernivtsi-children-s-hospital</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://ukrainians.nl/modern-medical-equipment-delivered-to-chernivtsi-children-s-hospital"><![CDATA[<p>The Ukrainians in the Netherlands Foundation has donated a
state-of-the-art automated blood culture system (bacteriological
hemocultivator) worth €17,500 to the Chernivtsi Regional Children’s
Clinical Hospital (ОКНП "Чернівецька обласна дитяча клінічна
лікарня").</p>

<p>🩸 This automated bacteriological hemocultivator is one of the core
diagnostic tools for multidisciplinary hospitals. It plays a vital role
in improving the quality and efficiency of medical care, reducing the
number of complications and lowering mortality rates among patients with
sepsis and fevers of unknown origin.</p>

<p>The device works by analysing blood samples where, in severe infections,
microorganisms may multiply. Its use allows for the rapid diagnosis of
sepsis in young patients, enabling doctors to prescribe timely and
effective treatment.</p>

<p>– The pathogen can be detected within the first 24 hours of testing.</p>

<p>– A negative result is confirmed by day 5.</p>

<p>– In contrast, manual diagnosis can take up to 10 days — meaning this
system cuts diagnostic time in half.</p>

<p>This life-saving technology will directly impact the lives of vulnerable
children in the region — and we are proud to support Ukrainian
healthcare institutions with such critical tools.</p>

<p>We extend our heartfelt thanks to our generous donors and to Alena Boer,
whose support helped make this delivery possible.</p>

<p>Together, we save lives. Together, we support Ukraine.</p>

<p><strong><em>– August 15, 2024</em></strong></p>

<p><img src="/assets/img/events/2024-08-15-modern-medical-equipment-delivered-to-chernivtsi-children-s-hospital/media/image2.jpg" class="img-thumbnail margined" /></p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="humanitarian" /><category term="humanitarian" /><category term="aid" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[The Ukrainians in the Netherlands Foundation has donated a state-of-the-art automated blood culture system (bacteriological hemocultivator) worth €17,500 to the Chernivtsi Regional Children’s Clinical Hospital (ОКНП "Чернівецька обласна дитяча клінічна лікарня").]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">De jaarrekening van de Stichting</title><link href="https://ukrainians.nl/jaarrekening" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="De jaarrekening van de Stichting" /><published>2023-12-11T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-12-11T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://ukrainians.nl/jaarrekening</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://ukrainians.nl/jaarrekening"><![CDATA[<div class="row text-center">
<div class="col-12 mt-50">

<a href="https://ukrainians.nl/assets/pdf/Publicatiestukken.pdf" style="
border-radius: var(--border-radius);
border: 1px solid var(--text-color);
color: var(--text-color);
padding: 1em;
margin: 1em;
">
<i class="far fa-file-pdf" style="font-size: 2em;"></i>&nbsp; De jaarrekening van de Stichting
</a>

</div>

<div class="col-12 mt-50">

<a href="https://ukrainians.nl/assets/pdf/Balans-en-staat-van-baten-en-lasten-2022.pdf" style="
border-radius: var(--border-radius);
border: 1px solid var(--text-color);
color: var(--text-color);
padding: 1em;
margin: 1em;
">
<i class="far fa-file-pdf" style="font-size: 2em;"></i>&nbsp; Balans en staat van baten en lasten 2022
</a>

</div>
</div>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="press" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[]]></summary></entry></feed>